Guide to the Adeline Burr Davis Green Papers, 1796-1956
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Adeline Burr Davis Green papers 1796-1956
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Green, Adeline Burr Davis, 1843-1931.
5.0 Linear Feet 1551 Items
Married first to David Davis, lawyer, Supreme Court Justice, and U.S. Senator from Illinois, and then to Wharton Jackson Green, agriculturist and U.S. Representative from North Carolina; resident of Fayetteville, N.C.
Personal and family correspondence. Includes journal of and letters, 1851-1853, from brother James M. Burr to his wife describing his life in California during the Gold Rush; Civil War letters to Adeline from her cousin (and later second husband), Wharton Jackson Green, while a prisoner-of-war at Johnson's Island, Ohio; letters, 1882-1885, from first husband David Davis describing daily proceedings in the Senate, social functions in Washington, D.C., and notable persons; letters from friends of Davis concerning personal and political matters; letters, 1906-1928, from Jessica Randolph Smith and others pertaining to the United Daughters of the Confederacy; and letters, 1911-1931, from cousin James Henry Rice, Jr., ornithologist, naturalist, editor, and literary figure, discussing politics, conservation, South Carolina culture, world affairs, especially relative to Germany and Russia, his rice plantations, and the League of Nations.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Adeline Burr Davis Green Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1944-1962.
Biographical Note
Married first to David Davis, lawyer, Supreme Court Justice, and U.S. Senator from Illinois, and then to Wharton Jackson Green, agriculturist and U.S. Representative from North Carolina; resident of Fayetteville, N.C.
Collection Overview
Papers of Adeline E. (Burr) Davis Green (1843-1931) include letters, 1851-1853, from James M. Burr, brother of Adeline (Burr) Davis Green, to his wife describing his life in California searching for gold; James Burr's journal entitled "Journal of a Cruise to California and the Diggins"; Civil War letters from her second husband and cousin, Wharton Jackson Green (1831-1910), later agriculturist and U.S. congressman, while a prisoner-of-war at Johnson's Island, Ohio; letters, 1882-1885, from her first husband, David Davis (1815-1886), jurist and U. S. senator, describing daily proceedings in the senate, social functions in Washington, D.C., and notable persons; letters from friends of Davis concerning personal and political matters; letters, 1906-1928, from Jessica Randolph Smith and others pertaining to the Daughters of the Confederacy; and letters, 1911-1931, from James Henry Rice, Jr. (1868-1935), ornithologist, naturalist, editor, and literary figure, discussing politics, conservation, South Carolina culture, world affairs, especially relative to Germany and Russia, his rice plantations, and the League of Nations.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Burr, James M.
Davis, David, 1815-1886
Green, Wharton J. (Wharton Jackson), 1831-1910
Rice, James Henry, 1868-1935
Smith, Jessica Randolph
Johnson Island Prison
League of Nations
United Daughters of the Confederacy
Plantations -- South Carolina
Politicians' spouses -- Southern States
Rice -- South Carolina
Soldiers -- Confederate States of America -- Correspondence
Legislators -- United States
California -- Description and travel
South Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
South Carolina -- Social life and customs
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Prisoners and prisons
Washington (D.C.) -- Social life and customs
Fayetteville (N.C.)
Contents of Collection
- Letters, 1814-1956 and undated, (4 boxes)
  - Letters, 1814-1883, March (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1883, April-1886 (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1887-1919 (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1920-1956 and undated (Box 4)
- Miscellany, 1796-1931 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - Miscellany, 1796-1931 (Box 4)
  - Invitations, calling cards, and menus (Box 5)
- Volumes, 1851-1900s and undated, (1 box)
  - Diary of James M. Burr, 1851-1858 (Box 5)
    "Journal of a cruise to California and the Digging, kept by James M. Burr, Boston, Mass. or Como, Whiteside Co., Illinois"
  - List of companies attended and given since coming to Bloomington, June 1883-1886
  - Miscellaneous notebook, 1900s
  - Copybook (A.E. Green)
  - Autograph book
  - Ledger with miscellaneous notes, 1899-1900s
- Printed material and clippings, undated, (2 boxes)
  - Printed materials and clippings (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
- Pictures, undated, (2 boxes)
  Most images are portraits, and most are labeled.
  - Pictures (Box 8)
  - Pictures (Box 9)